Guide to the Frederick William Hotchkiss Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Frederick William Hotchkiss papers
1783-1844
MS 974
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
Sermons, prayers, records of the First Church of Saybrook, Connecticut (1783-1844), memorandum books, a few items of correspondence, and materials relating to a private school that Frederick Hotchkiss conducted in his house. The records of the First Church and the memorandum books are available in photostatic copies from a microfilm of the originals.
Hotchkiss, Frederick William, 1762-1844
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frederick Sheffield, 1941-1942.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Original and photostatic materials pertaining to Frederick William Hotchkiss and to his parish, the First Church of Saybrook, Connecticut, make up this collection. The original documents include four copies of the Articles of Faith and the church covenant of First Church, a selection of sermons, addresses, and prayers by Hotchkiss (1787-1838), and a small notebook of letters from Hotchkiss to William Tully, Jr. (1802-1807). Supplementing these items are photostatic copies of records of First Church (1783-1844), further writings by Hotchkiss (1802-1844), and several memorandum books. These copies were made from a microfilm of the original documents belonging to Frederick Sheffield. He donated the Frederick William Hotchkiss Papers to Yale University in 1941-1942, and gave the microfilm to the Connecticut State Library.
Biographical / Historical
Frederick William Hotchkiss, the fifth of seven children of John Hotchkiss (Yale 1748) and Susanna (Jones) Hotchkiss, was born in New Haven on October 30, 1762, and was baptized on the following day. An elder brother was graduated here in 1774.
During the invasion of New Haven by the British on July 4, 1779, he acted as an aid to the officer who commanded the force raised in resistance. In this conflict his father and two of his uncles were slain.
For four years after graduation he taught school,--during the latter part of the time in Wethersfield, Connecticut. Meantime he studied theology, and he was licensed to preach by the Hartford South Association of Ministers in October, 1782.
Early in the following month he began to supply the pulpit in Saybrook, Connecticut, where the Rev. William Hart (Yale 1732) had been for six months disabled from preaching. He soon received a unanimous invitation to settle as colleague-pastor, but owing to his consciousness of inexperience he deferred compliance with the repeated requests of this people for several months, and was finally ordained on September 24, 1783, over a church of 69 members.
The senior pastor died in July, 1784, and Mr. Hotchkiss remained in sole charge of the society until June, 1838, when in response to his own request a colleague was settled. During this ministry over six hundred persons had been admitted to the church. He continued in office until his death, in Saybrook, after three days' illness, on March 31, 1844, in his 82d year.
He was married, on August 29, 1790, by the Rev. Richard Ely, of Westbrook, to Amelia Hart, the youngest child of his predecessor in office, who died on August 8, 1845, aged 84 ½ years. Their children were two daughters, who survived them.
Father Hotchkiss, as he was called, was an ideally faithful pastor, and an affectionate, fervent preacher of practical righteousness. His voice was of almost phenomenal strength. Besides his other labors, for a number of years he taught a private school in his own house, at which some thirty young men were fitted for College.
(Taken from Yale College Biographical Sketches, 1778).
Education -- Connecticut -- Saybrook; Sermons; Clergy; Hotchkiss, Frederick William, 1762-1844; First Church of Christ (Saybrook, Conn.)
- Inventory
  - Articles of Faith and Church Covenant, Saybrook [4 copies], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sermons, 1787-1795 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Valedictory address before the First Church and Congregation of Saybrook, 1838 January 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Prayers for the Superior Court of Haddam, 1803, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Prayers for special occasions, and other set pieces, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Records of the First Church, Saybrook [photostatic copy], 1783-1844 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sermon, "On the contemplation of an aged Pastor on the completion of the sixtieth year of his ministry," Saybrook [photostatic copy], 1843 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Reflections Nativitatus [photostatic copy], 1802-1844 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memorandum book [photostatic copy], 1815-1844 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Names of young gentlemen educated for college..." and memorandum book [photostatic copy], 1843 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters from FWH to William Tully, Jr. [original and photostatic copy], 1802-1807 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Arithmetic book [photostatic copy], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ALS Caroline E. Moore to Frederick Sheffield relating to FWH mss. [photostatic copy], 1912 February 7 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Clippings of obituaries, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)